<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity &amp; extent of the obligation, with the manner &amp; measures of restitution in a sermon preached the 9th of October, 1681, before the corporation of Haverford-West, at Saint Mary's in Haverford / by William Williams ...</title>
            <author>Williams, William, Minister of St. Mary's in Haverford.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12642495</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12642495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 338:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity &amp; extent of the obligation, with the manner &amp; measures of restitution in a sermon preached the 9th of October, 1681, before the corporation of Haverford-West, at Saint Mary's in Haverford / by William Williams ...</title>
                  <author>Williams, William, Minister of St. Mary's in Haverford.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for Thomas Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIX, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65035:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Neceſſity &amp; Extent</hi> Of the OBLIGATION, With the Manner &amp; Meaſures OF Reſtitution, IN A SERMON, Preached the 9th. of <hi>October,</hi> 1681. Before the Corporation of <hi>Haverford-Weſt,</hi> at Saint <hi>Mary's</hi> in <hi>Haverford.</hi> By <hi>William Williams, <hi>A. M.</hi>
               </hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Mary's</hi> in <hi>Haverford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65035:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65035:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THe Deſign of the Publication of the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is meerly ſhewing to the World, it is not quite ſo monſtrous a Thing upon all Accounts, as ſome People (who I ſuppoſe, thought it their Intereſt; and therefore) made it their Buſineſs to have it believed. Whatever there be in the Compoſure, that may ſtand in need of an Apology; if the Reader's Candor, with ſuch To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks as the Corporation wherein it was Delivered, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being as Plain, and Particular as might be, where there is an eſpecial Faculty of Tranſlating of Crimes, where the Matter is otherwiſe Ordered (as by good Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, I dare aſſure the Reader there was, where this was Delivered) do not help him to me; I hold it not Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence out of a deſign of foreſtalling all the Objections that might be made againſt it, either to furniſh the Ignorant, and prejudiced Reader with ſuch as he would never elſe himſelf ſtart; and will be ſure never to have Kindneſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (however it may fare with his Underſtanding) to take along the Anſwers to, or give the Candid and Ingenious One the trouble of Reading Anſwers to Objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:65035:3"/> I am ſure he will never make.</p>
            <p>To me it will be Satisfaction, that this Diſcourſe will Manifeſt it ſelf not to be really as bad as it is Repreſented. It Contends not for Eminency of Strength or Beauty, but againſt the Imputation of ſtrange Weakneſs and Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: the Confutation of the Charge, whereof I have been Reſolved to make, is of the Nature of the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's</hi> to the Diſputant againſt Motion, by making the Thing walk before it; and ſo let it paſs with this one Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, by way of Advertiſement, That</p>
            <p>An honeſt Gentleman, one Mr. <hi>Richard Jones,</hi> of the Town it was Delivered in, was ſo far (as hath been Alleadged) from putting me upon a Diſcourſe of this Nanure, that he, nor more, nor ſooner, knew of the Purpoſe of it, than thoſe that Conceived themſelves moſt Concerned in it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65035:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Neceſſity &amp; Meaſures</hi> OF RESTITUTION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 19.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If I have taken any Thing from any Man by falſe Accuſation, I Reſtore him Four-fold.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words, I do from this Place (which, I hope, may add Weight and Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and gain Credit to my Proteſt) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, for the Occaſion they Naturally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to urge a <hi>Matter of Conſcience,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Neceſſary to be Urged here, I have long ſince (ſince I could not longer ſhut up my Eyes againſt what ſo Manifeſtly offered it ſelf) entertained Thoughts, next a Reſolution, ſome time or other, to inſiſt upon: That I did not do it ſooner, ſome plauſible Reaſons to the world I could offer; upon the Acceptance whereof, yet in <hi>God</hi>'s Sight I dare not much preſume; yet Hope,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65035:4"/> and beg His merciful Pardon for it. But now being ſomething in the ſtate of a Dying Man, taking my leave of concernments of courſe of this Nature, in this Place; I am Reſolved, by <hi>God</hi>'s Grace, with that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality and Sincerity, which the Conſideration of my Great <hi>God,</hi> before whom, I muſt one day give Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my Charge, and that Uprightneſs that muſt give Eaſe to my Conſcience, may require to Diſcharge my ſelf, That, if I Live to ſee the Curſes, ſuch Sins are Obnoxious to, poured out upon this place, or any particular Perſon here, or his Poſterity, or that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the State of final Impenitency any Perſon may Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry by, I may have no Remorſe from Conſcience, for being Acceſſary to it by my Silence; no occaſion to Charge my ſelf for not Repreſenting the true Eſtate of the Matter, and not doing what I could to prevent their Temporal and Eternal Ruin: Wherein, though my Commiſſion ſeems to run ſomething in the Strain of <hi>Ezekiels, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. &amp;c. <hi>Son of Man, I ſend thee to a Rebellious Nation, to an Impudent Children, and ſtiff Hearted,</hi> &amp;c. and my Doom may be for my Meſſage, if it lye in the Power of ſome, that of <hi>Jeremiah's,</hi> the Dungeon; yet I hope, by <hi>God</hi>'s Grace, I may have ſome Portion of the ſame Courage <hi>God</hi> required in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel,</hi> not to be afraid of Mens Words; Though Briers and Thorns be with me, though I dwell among Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, I will not be afraid of their Words, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed at their Looks; but when I have given my Propoſition from the Text, deduced it to an Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Guilty Conſcience of any Perſon here,</p>
            <p>Then you may perceive, the Words are the Speech of one, newly and fully Converted in the Judgement of our Saviour; who in the next Verſe declares upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65035:4"/> it, that Salvation is come into his Houſe; which the Learned <hi>Hammond</hi> Parapraiſes, <hi>This day Repentance, and ſo the Mercies of the Goſpel are come to</hi> Zaccheus. They are the Words of a Publican, one imployed in the Gathering of a Tax, impoſed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Power, which Miniſtred him occaſion for diminiſhing, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Right of poor People, that either for the greatneſs of his Strength and Intereſt, or the meanneſs of their own, were not able to Right themſelves; for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Word rendered here, <hi>I have taken by Falſe Accuſation,</hi> in the Judgement of the beſt <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians,</hi> may import the <hi>Act of Fraud,</hi> by what Means ſoever contrived, or in what matter ſoever Exerciſed; and that <hi>Falſe Accuſation</hi> put in here, to clear the Sence of it, doth not render it inextenſible to the Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſome Men in this place, will appear, if (which you ought) you conſider, That every wrong Defence in ſuch a Caſe, is in effect, a <hi>Falſe Accuſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition from the Text, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Reſtitution, in caſes of</hi> Fraud and Injury, <hi>is ſo neceſſarily a Concomitant of true Repentance, that in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of</hi> Fraud and Injuries, <hi>where there is not Reſtitution made to the very utmoſt of the Defrauding or Injurious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Power, in all Circumſtances that may ſignify the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs of his Repentance, for his</hi> Fraud and Injuries, <hi>the Fraudulent and Injurious Perſon cannot be Saved,</hi> i. e. <hi>muſt be inevitably Damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to the clearing of this Propoſition, I hope it is ſo known a Truth (that a Sinner, as long as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues Unrepenting, cannot be Saved; and if he Dyes in any unrepented Sin, is inevitably Damned) that I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65035:5"/> need not give my ſelf the trouble to Prove it. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was that St. <hi>John</hi> called for, before his Baptiſm: It was that our Saviour himſelf indiſpenſibly required; it is that which His Apoſtles after him did; it is (and for the greateſt Reaſons in the World, as were it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Neceſſary here, could be ſhewed) That, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, to any perſon of Maturity, the Goſpel doth no where Promiſe any of its Benefits, or any of its Mercies; nay, tells us Poſitively, <hi>That unleſs we Repent we ſhall All likewiſe Periſh; and that no Man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Holineſs</hi> (which ſuppoſes Repentance) <hi>ſhall ſee the Face of the Lord.</hi> And therefore being ſo clear to, and undeniable a Truth by, any Chriſtian, I ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fall to make good the Propoſition ſuppoſed in the Text; That <hi>Reſtitution</hi> is ſo much a Note of true Repentance, that without making it, no Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to make it, can be Saved; that is, as before, That <hi>Reſtitution</hi> in caſes of <hi>Fraud and Injuries,</hi> is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily a Concomitant of true Repentance, that in caſes of <hi>Fraud and Injuries,</hi> where there is not <hi>Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> made to the very Utmoſt of the Defrauding or Injurious Perſon's Power, in all Circumſtances that may ſignify the Seriouſneſs of his Repentance for his <hi>Fraud and Injuries:</hi> the Fraudulent and Injurious perſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Saved, <hi>i. e.</hi> muſt be inevitably Damned. Which I ſhall, <hi>Firſt,</hi> clear in general, from the Nature of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Shew in what manner, and how far (in ſeveral Caſes) <hi>Reſtitution</hi> is to be made; and Proceed according to my Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Repentance hath (by All) been judged of ſo great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, indeed of ſo abſolute a Neceſſity, that Divines of all Perſwaſions, Ancient, and Modern, have been Curious, and laid out a great deal of Time and Pains
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65035:5"/> in diſcovering and ſtating of the Nature of it. The Moment Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> apprehended; the Underſtanding of it, he expreſſes in theſe Words, <hi>Si quid autem in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ Religione ſcire noſtrâ refert, id certe maxime refert, nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe intelligere ac probe tenere quâ ratione, quâ lege, quâ conditione, quâ facilitate aut difficultate obtineatur peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Remiſſio. If there be any thing in the whole Courſe of Religion worth our Underſtanding; that is certainly moſt ſo,</hi> viz. <hi>to underſtand, and rightly comprehend, which way, upon what terms and condition remiſſion or forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sins may be obtained,</hi> Cal. inſtit. l. 3. c. 4. which is as much as if he had ſaid, The nature of Repentance; He Sub-joyns there his reaſon from the Reſtleſneſs the Conſcience muſt be ſubject to, under a disſatisfaction touching the Nature of it: But after all the large Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes laid out upon it, as often as it comes in the ways of Controvertiſts; or Men that inſiſt upon it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, and immediately to move Men to the Practice of it, and Obſervation of the Words; whereby it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Holy Scripture, and Practices of Men noted in it, for an accepted <hi>repentance:</hi> the juſt Collection is, That <hi>repentance</hi> implies a thorough change of the Heart of the Sinner, fully deteſting his former Sins, and reſolving, for the future, to lead a new Life, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the good Pleaſure of his GOD. This De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of former Sins, by the School-men is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be attended with, nay, practiſed in theſe Three Inſtances, <hi>Contrition or Compunction of Heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus li. 4. Diſt. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Confeſſion with the Mouth, and Satisfaction in Act or Deed.</hi> All (or either whereof) the <hi>Reformiſts</hi> are ſo far from taking away, or denying, That they ſeem only to rid them from the corrupt Gloſſes, the Propugnators of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> perſwaſion blinded, and led by Intereſt, put upon them.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65035:6"/>
            <p>The forementioned Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> when he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſence of Contrition, or ſorrow of Heart, finds Fault with their requiring ſuch a juſt Proportion of it, as may be anſwerable, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate to the nature and degrees of the Crime, which muſt create a great deal of trouble to the Sinner, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a proportionable meaſure of Contrition or Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row enjoyned, but not determined; but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſays, <hi>Equidem ſedulo &amp; acriter instandum eſſe fateor, ut quiſque amare deſtendo ſua peccata, ſe ad eorum diſplicentiam &amp; odium magis acuat; Haec enim eſt non paenitenda triſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, quae paenitentiam gignit in Salutem,</hi> ib. <hi>I confeſs tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it is to be carefully and earneſtly Urged, That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one by bitterly lamenting his Sins, may more egg him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a diſpleaſure with, and hatred of his Sin; for this is Sorrow not to Repented of, which worketh Repentance to Salvation:</hi> And a little further, <hi>Diximus &amp; nos quodam loco nunquam ſine paenitentiâ obvenire peccatorum Remiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quod nulli niſi afflicti &amp; peccatorum Conſcientiâ vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerati Dei miſericordiam implorare ſincere poſſunt: And I my ſelf, have one where ſaid, That without Repentance, there is never any remiſſion of Sins; becauſe that none but ſuch as are afflicted, and wounded with the Conſciouſneſs of their Sins, can ſincerely implore God's Mercy.</hi> In both which Clauſes, he not only allows of, but requires Sorrow for Sin; only in the former he complains of the unreaſonableneſs of enjoyning, and not determining the certain Proportion due for every Sin; and after the latter of thoſe two cited places, ſayes, He taught the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Non in ſuam compunctionem, neque in ſuas lachrymas intueri, ſed utrumque oculum in ſolam Domini Miſericordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am defigere. Not to look back upon his Compunction and Tears, but faſten his Eyes upon the alone Mercy of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65035:6"/> Lord:</hi> In ſhort (as in all reaſon he ſhould) Sorrow, and an hearty Sorrow for Sin, he not only allows, but judges neceſſary, only would not have Men rely upon it, as meriting Pardon; but be naturally neceſſary in order to it: the Sinner, without it being not qualified for Mercy, for as much as a ſenſe of the miſery of his Condition, muſt be an Incentive to his applying of himſelf to <hi>God</hi> for Pardon.</p>
            <p>Then for Confeſſion,<note place="margin">Cal. inſtit. li. 3. c. 4. <hi>parte de Confeſ.</hi>
               </note> he doth not abſolutely deny the uſefulneſs and neceſſity of it, but ties the neceſſity of an acknowledgement of our Sins to <hi>God;</hi> which when it is ſincere, he ſayes,<note n="*" place="margin">Sequitur vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria apud homines confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio, quoties id vel divinae Gloriae, vel Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliationis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae intereſt.</note> will be followed by a voluntary one to Men, as often as the Glory of God, and a Man's own Humiliation may be promoted by it: And the Uſefulneſs of it to ſome certain Perſons, for ſome certain Purpoſes he<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid.</note> determines differently from the <hi>Church of Rome:</hi> All which having been not long ſince, by our Right Reverend <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> accounted for from this place, I ſhall ſay no more to it now; But proceed to that which the Text, and my preſent Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe more directly lead me to, the Conſideration of the <hi>Third</hi> Concomitant of, or inſtance whereby our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of Sin is to be Diſcovered, Satisfaction; which indeed, all <hi>Reformists</hi> in the notion the Maſter of the Sentences, and the <hi>School-men</hi> uſe it, for forcing of Penances upon perſons, as to the neceſſity of it, with relation to <hi>God,</hi> do generally, and for good reaſons diſclaim; I mean, as by it, the <hi>Romiſts</hi> do mean unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling of the Vice, and making <hi>God</hi> Satisfaction for every degree of Sin, by proportionable Degrees, and anſwerableneſs of the contrary Vertue; becauſe that ſuppoſition evacuates the neceſſity of Chriſt's Suffering for Men: But as it relates to the Church, and may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65035:7"/> be a Mean to ſatisfy the Members of it, of the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſinners Repentance; they do not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but judge it very convenient. But as by Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction may be meant Reſtitution, Amends made by the offending or injuring Perſon, to the Offended or Injured, as far as it may poſſibly lye in the power of the offending Perſon, they do all joyn in the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of it; and particularly the <hi>Church of England</hi> in its Exhortation upon the bidding of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> moves Men in order to their ſhewing themſelves true Penitents (which they ſhould be before they preſume to partake of That) to it. And St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is very clear and poſitive, <hi>Peccatum non remittitur niſi restitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ablatum. The Sin continues Unpardoned, till ſuch time as what is taken away, or</hi> (which is the ſame thing) <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly detained, be Reſtored.</hi> And common reaſon tells us, That if the taking what is another's, upon terms the right Owner conſents not to, muſt be a Sin, the keeping muſt be ſo too.</p>
            <p>But ſince the fore-ſight of Beggery, or the ſhame of acknowledging ſuch a Guilt, which the injurious Perſon may apprehend muſt follow a due Reſtitution of what is taken or detained: Since Covetouſneſs, and Pride, and Ambition, may be of ſo much more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with ſuch a Sinner, than the Voice of all the School-men, and Fathers in the World, the Church he lives in, and his own Reaſon; ſince thoſe Sins will, in all likelyhood, ſoon prevail with him: To conclude, from the poſſibility that all thoſe may err, that they really, and actually do ſo; ſince, I ſay, the foreſight of Beggery, that may enſue a Reſtitution; ſince the ſhame of ſuch an acknowledgement, as it muſt imply; ſince Covetouſneſs, Pride, and Ambition ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65035:7"/> with the Arts and Induſtry of a wicked Spirit, will likely ſoon frame in the Mind of the injuring Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuch a Diſcourſe as this, Grant that all theſe, this Preacher mentions, the Fathers, the School-men, and generally all Writers, Antient and Modern, (which yet we have but his word for) the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and my own Reaſon for the preſent, agree in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Reſtitution,</hi> as being that, without which, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance cannot be ſincere and entire; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without which, a Man that hath taken away or detained from one or more Perſons, or a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty their Right, cannot be ſaved; yet it being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that all of them may err in any point; ſo they may in this; and therefore I am not ſure they do not; and this ſhall have no Force upon me. Since an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this nature may be ſo Eluded, let us try the Force of ſuch as may be drawn from Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which, there can be Colour for offering any ſuch Evaſion.</p>
            <p>Now, that the ſence of Holy Scripture touching this matter, is the ſame, That there can be no true and perfect Repentance, without Reſtitution of what is Injuriouſly taken or detained, will, I hope, be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſufficiently proved, if I can from it prove, That he that doth not make Reſtitution of what he hath wrongfully taken away or detained, is Guilty of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the whole Law. Certainly, he that, in <hi>God</hi>'s Judgement, is guilty of Tranſgreſſing the whole Law, cannot be thought to be a true Penitent; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, as long as he is not ſo, cannot be Saved. And either non-Reſtitution muſt be no Sin at all, or in the judgement of St. <hi>James, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 10. it is a Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole Law; for there he ſaith plainly,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65035:8"/> 
               <hi>Whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet Offend in one point, he is Guilty of all;</hi> and in the following Verſe gives the reaſon of it. Now there is no ſort of poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of avoiding this Charge, but by the effrontery of denying it to be a Sin: To ſuch a one as ſhould be ſo ſhameleſs as to ſuſpect, much more deny, That the not Reſtoring of what is wrongfully detained from others is a Sin; I'd ask him, What he thinks makes Theft a Sin? Is it the taking away, by one, what he hath no right to? It is ſo here, when a perſon takes that which is not his Right, and keeps it longer than he ſhould; or, Is it only the Violence uſed to the perſon in the Act; Not ſo, for ſome Stealths are without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered the perſons, from whom it is made: Nay, the detaining of others Rights againſt their declared Wills, or becauſe they dare declare nothing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, increaſes the numbers of the Thefts, with the numbers of the Minutes, whereby the Detainer's time is told: <hi>Three</hi> Hours not reſtoring what ought to be Reſtored, is ſo many Hours Stealing in the ſence of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and Reaſon: But that I do not only ſay it is, but ſhew <hi>God's</hi> Sentence of it, as a Sin. See in the 33d. of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> how he particularizes Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as the means of looſening of a Sin, and ſign of Converſion of a Sinner, which he had not, if in his Judgement, keeping another's Right, had been no Sin; for after he had ſaid in the 14th. <hi>verſe, Again, when I ſay unto the Wicked, Thou ſhalt ſurely Dye: if he turn from his Sin, and do that which is Lawful and Right,</hi> he Exemplifies doing Lawful and Right, in the 15th. <hi>ver.</hi> by, <hi>If the Wicked restore the Pledge, give again that he had Robbed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he ſhall ſurely Live, and ſhall not Dye. If the Wicked restore the Pledge, give again that he had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65035:8"/> Robbed:</hi> Wicked then, it ſeems he was in <hi>God's</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment while he kept it.</p>
            <p>If after all this it ſhould be ſaid, That <hi>Penitence</hi> is an inward Act of the Mind, <hi>Reſtitution</hi> an outward Expreſſion; and that <hi>God</hi> regardeth the Inwards, and lays not ſo much Streſs upon outward Actions. I'd ask the perſon, Whether he would be ſo Cheated? Such a Fool as to believe, that an <hi>High-way</hi> Robber that takes his Purſe, would by ever ſo much ſolemn Declarations of his Sorrow, for the Injury he had done, make him believe he were truly Sorry, while he ſaw his Purſe in his hand? What <hi>God</hi>'s eſtimate of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency is, we may judge by St. <hi>John</hi>'s calling upon thoſe that came to his Baptiſm, to <hi>Bring forth Fruit meet for Repentance;</hi> by our <hi>Saviour's</hi> declaration, <hi>That we might know Men by their Fruit;</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> challenging of the ſincere Believer, which alſo muſt be a true Penitent, to <hi>Shew his Faith by his Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſo ſhewed, and I hope Convincingly, the indiſpenſableneſs of Reſtitution, from injurious Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in general; I come now to repreſent the extent of the Concernment of it; And that as to Perſons, and Things, with the meaſures or degrees of Reſtitution, that ought to be made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to Perſons, Where the Queſtion is, <hi>How far this Guilt of not Restitution, or not Reſtoring what is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly taken or detained, may extend it's ſelf? Whether the Guilt dies with the Perſon that did at first do the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and never made Amends for it, or touches his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, that they become Guilty of it? And if it do, How far, and what obligation of Reſtitution it lays upon them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which, I thus Anſwer, That, that <hi>Declaration</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65035:9"/> Almighty <hi>God</hi> made in the <hi>Second Commandment,</hi> That He would <hi>Viſit the Iniquity of the Fathers upon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> is very general; becauſe it is to the Children of all them that hate Him, that is, not only to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of them that Worſhip the Hoſt of Heaven, as ſome of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did; or any thing upon Earth, or the Water under the Earth, or the Images of any of them; but ſuch as preferred any thing before Him; that Preference of a Thing, being counted an hatred of Him; becauſe it ſuppoſes an incompetency of Love to Him. And if ſo, ſure to them that gratify their Luſt or Covetouſneſs, their Pride and Ambition; or any Sin proceeding from them; or any thing elſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever contrary to <hi>God's</hi> clear Commands: I ſay, This Declaration which <hi>God</hi> there made ſo general, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abſolutely repealed. In <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> indeed, we find, That to the <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> that had taken (upon the Execution likely of this part of the Law) up a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, that <hi>The Fathers had Eaten ſowr Grapes; and that the Childrens Teeth were ſet on Edge,</hi> God promiſes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that looks like the Contrary: The Reaſon and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port whereof, yet may probably be this, That the Sins of that Age, of the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking, that when <hi>God</hi> Avenged them to the full, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Recollection, and juſt Examination of themſelves, they might find no reaſon to think, that there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny need from the heap of their Father's Treſpaſſes, to take in any, to aggravate their Sins, and ſo bring down a greater proportion of Judgement; but that their own, every Man's ſingly, or the preſent Communities might be ſufficient to provoke more Judgements, than they ſaw Executed upon them; or elſe, That their Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations had been, and were ſo great, that whereas <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65035:9"/> formerly had, in ſome caſes, ſuſpended the Execution of a Vengeance due upon the Father's Treſpaſſes, to the time of his Poſterity, as he did in the caſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab,</hi> That he would not then ſhew ſo much Mercy, but Puniſh as faſt as they Offended; but whether for ſuch, or ſome other Reaſon, He did to the <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> for ſome ſeaſon, determine it ſhould be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; yet that he did finally and univerſally, that is, That he did for ever reſolve, and to all People, that it ſhould be otherwiſe, doth no ways, and no where appear; but the contrary by the Obſervation of all Ages.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee, That whatever the Sin of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be, his Children have no warrant from Holy Scripture, other than the firſt Sinner had, that they will eſcape the Puniſhment, that is, have no other Warrant, no Condition than Repentance; and that a true ſincere One, attended with all the genuine Fruit and Effects of it; but on the other ſide, <hi>God's</hi> Truth that can never fail, to aſſure them they may be Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon for the Sins of the Father; and for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to inquire, ſince <hi>God</hi> hath made no Diſcovery, would be a ſinful, and uſeleſs Curioſity. When he ſaies, He will do a thing, we may aſſure our ſelves, He will find a way to do it: But whatever mitigation the Children of other Sinners may have of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, ſurely he that comes into the unjuſt Poſſeſſion of his Father, as ſuch, will have none; for look whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath in his Subſtance derived from his Father, more than he would have had in caſe his Father had done all Right, paid all their own; ſo much hath he that was not his Fathers, and conſequently more than his Father could juſtly Derive to him: And his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65035:10"/> a Poſſeſſion of them, doth not only entail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Vengeance denounced in the <hi>Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> which, if he had had none of thoſe unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Poſſeſſions from his Father, he had been obnoxious to, but doubles it by practiſing and continuing in the Sin. His Father's Sin was detaining unjuſtly another's, and he Succeeds him, as his Son naturally without that liable to the Puniſhment, and as continuing the Sin, in his own perſon. And be ſure the Guilt (tho the ſence of it may) doth not leſſen, the longer the Sin is practiſed, but increaſes with time, and the Advantage made of it; For ſee how much the firſt wrong quick ſtock hath advanced any Man's Eſtate, above what it would have been without it; ſo much it might have advanced the right Owner's, if he had not been Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and conſequently, ſo much ought to be Reſtored to the laſt Mite of a Man's Poſſeſſion; which if it do not riſe to a full Reſtitution, it ought to be Weighed out as much as poſſibly he can in Sorrow before <hi>God,</hi> for the Injuries (which, if he had been able, he ought to have teſtified by a full Reſtitution) by his hearty Prayers to <hi>God</hi> to make the injured perſon Amends; and his Recommendation of him to ſuch Men as he can influence, that are of Ability to make him: nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in order to Reſtitution, ought a Man to take his meaſures from the Advantage himſelf hath made of things wrongfully Detained; but account upon the beſt Husbandry could be uſed about them. This I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a clear and full Solution of the Queſtion propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with this notice, That what I ſaid of the Son of the firſt Offender, muſt be applyed to all continuing the unjuſt Poſſeſſion, and making Advantages of it, proportionably to the Advantages they have, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65035:10"/> right Owner might have made of it, in ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>Now I come more particularly to the things a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may injure, and be injured in:</p>
            <p>They are Goods, or Body, or Name, or All.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Goods we know comprehend all the Poſſeſſions, or things a Man may have Right to, a Propriety, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, for the ſupport and comfort of Men, <hi>God</hi> hath appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and himſelf given general Rules for the determination of. The keeping of Money, or Land, or any Thing elſe, whatſoever of Right belonging to another, is a violation of Right, which muſt, (if a Man would be ſaved) be reſtored or amended, as I ſhewed before in the general.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Man may Injure, and be injured in his Body, ſeveral ways, by ſeveral perſons. In his Infancy, for want of due Care in the Nurture of it, (and ſo may the Mind alſo be Injured) or in his Maturity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Strength, either in part of his Body by being Maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſo, or in the whole by induſtrious Miniſtring of pernitious Diet or Phyſick, or vexation of Spirit; in all which, and the like caſes, are required all the Amends that may be from the offending Perſon, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the unhappineſſes ſuſtained by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by his Means; and that extended to his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to whom he might have been more uſeful, if he had not ſuſtained thoſe Wrongs in his Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The third thing wherein an Injury may be done a Perſon, is his good Name: A thing that <hi>Solomon</hi> pronounces generally Precious, but of mighty Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to ſome above others; as being that whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own, and their Families livelyhood do depend; nay, of ſo ill conſequence may the defamation of ſome perſons be, that it may in great Meaſures obſtruct the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65035:11"/> Salvation of many Souls, which (not to mince the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) may be in the caſe of a defamed Miniſter, whoſe Miniſtry is like to be more or leſs Succesful, the more or leſs blemiſhed Men render his Reputation. And if it be ſo, let a pretended Miſdemeanour, before a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Civil Magiſtrate, be compared with a real Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of a Miniſter, before, and to his Flock in numbers, and as far as may be ſingly be put into the Ballance, and ſee where the weight of Miſchief will lye; on that ſide where the Scandal indiſpoſes Men to receive Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit from a perſon to the Salvation of their Souls; or that, where the preſumed Miſdeameanour to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, can but occaſion a leſs Eſteem of one perſon: Or, (if it muſt be transferred to the Place and Office, as, where an intention to the contrary is declared, I do not ſee how it ſhould) but be of ſome ill example in point of Civil Obſervance, which yet Men in thoſe Stations are furniſhed with Authority ſufficient to reſtrain the ill conſequence of: As the World goes, where ill Fame ſpreads wideſt, and goes furtheſt, it is an hard matter to Preſcribe a way of full Compenſation in this Caſe: If we are ſure of the Deſert, and mean the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the perſon, the Guilt may abide at home, where the Occaſion dwells; but I ſay, where a good Name is traduced Groundleſly, and Unwarrantably, Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and Spleeniſhly, it may be morally impoſſible to make proportionable Amends; eſpecially, where the detraction is attended with the hazard of Souls: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, all the courſes that can be preſumed effectual to the purpoſe, are to be uſed towards the Reſtitution of a Man's good Name: And this, as in the other caſes, upon the greateſt penalty, Eternal Damnation.</p>
            <p>Now that all this is ſaid, and made good, it will,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65035:11"/> it may be, be judged Impertinent, and Unneceſſary, and Uncharitable, and as much more than all that comes to, as provoked Fancies may qualify ſome Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for Imagining and Expreſſing; If I do not give ſome reaſons for my Preſumption, that there are ſome perſons in my Congregation that are guilty of this Sin; the nature and danger whereof, I have endeavoured to Explicate: For indeed, it had been an abſurdity not to be accounted for, to have been large, and particular in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the nature and danger of intemperance, or impatience before <hi>Socrates,</hi> who, nor was, nor ever was like to be Guilty of either: And therefore, to rid my ſelf from the charge of ſuch another abſurdity in the choice of my Subject, and way of management of it; I'll give the reaſons that induce me to believe, there are ſome that hear me, notoriouſly Guilty of the groſs Sin I would amend, that is, wrongfully detaining the Rights of others; in Compaſſion to whoſe Souls (ſince I deſigned not to uſe many more) I thought fit to take hold of this Opportunity; in pity, I ſay, to their Souls, and to Acquit mine own from the Guilt, my finally ſilently paſſing by it, would Involve me in.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Reaſon I have to preſume, or rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſome of my Hearers Guilty of this unrepented, and if it continue ſo, unavoidably damnable Crime, is not of the leaſt Moment, of leſs Weight, than thoſe whereby <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath determined, and Men have unanimouſly uſed, as the means of deciding all Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, all matters of Doubt or Queſtion; The Oaths, I am told, of a competent number of Witneſſes, which to ſuſpect, before they be over-ruled by the Oaths of a more conſiderable number of more credible Perſons,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65035:12"/> and that determined ſo by a formal Sentence of Law, were not only Unreaſonable, but extreamly Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; and much more ſo, when the Charge has, as in the concernments of ſome, I am ſatisfied it hath been, by the proſecuted Parties own Acknowledgement, with a memorable Expreſſion, confeſſed. Nor was this Charge, which thus was made good, as I am convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, a Charge of meer miſimployment, (as ſome have much laboured to perſwade Strangers to their tempers and practices, to believe) or a Sum of Money promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be, but not returned, which I am told, was the ſingle Caſe of one, I am perſwaded too Honeſt, too much a Chriſtian to be rank'd with the Reſt; But of conſiderable groſs Sums not imployed at all. Now to make good the Truth of all this, there needs but the producing of the Depoſitions, which, if I liſted, I think, I might a Copy of; but that is more properly the concernment of a <hi>Court of Judicature:</hi> That ſuch Depoſitions upon Oath, were, ſeems too notorious a Truth: And if ſo, What remains, but that either there was ſuch a Guilt, or ſo many perſons as Swore it, are Perjured? Beloved, here is a clear Caſe, If one be free from the Charge of detaining another's Right, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comes within the guilt of Perjury; and ſo on the other ſide, If the charge of Detaining be Falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one, the charge of Perjury againſt the other muſt be true; And are either of theſe Sins to be ſoothed; to be paſt by in ſilence? Theſe ſure call for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the moſt ſignificant ſort. Is it not a ſad thing, that the Preacher muſt either not do what he ought; or bid the one go home, and Repent him of his Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and make haſt to ſignify the ſeriouſneſs, and reality of his Repentance by a ſpeedy Reſtitution; or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65035:12"/> bid the other go, and Repent his Perjury?</p>
            <p>Now to the former weighty Reaſon, which indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces me to believe ſome perſons here guilty of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, as without the utmoſt Reſtitution they can make, muſt become damnable; I have ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p>Any Perſon that tells me my ſelf, in a matter that I know due to me, that his own Conſcience having its full Liberty given it, cannot but tell him that it is ſo, that many others know, and none can with Truth deny; I ſay, any perſon that in ſuch a matter, by way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, in Confidence of the ſtrength of his Intereſt, or ought elſe, bids me come by all my Right as I can, unleſs I take what he pleaſes in full Satisfaction from a Company directly obliged to me for all; as for good Example, <hi>Ten Pounds</hi> for <hi>Thirty,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Twenty</hi> in one Year, without any proviſion for Amends for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, gives me great Reaſon to believe, that ſo many Men's Oaths in caſes of Injuries charged upon him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others, may not be Falſe; That Perſon that ſo convinces me, in a freſh injurious Act, gives me no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe, he could not poſſibly be Guilty of any of that Nature before.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third</hi> Thing that induces me to believe, all things are not as Right as they ſhould be with ſome perſons, is the Art and Diligence, I have obſerved, uſed in the forming and maintaining of a ſtrong Intereſt, and for ſome Years, ſecuring the Exerciſe of Government, in this place, in effect, in one hand: This indeed mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred ſome matter of Suſpicion, that the Affairs of ſome perſons might Suggeſt it neceſſary for them, by ſuch means to wave off the execution of a <hi>Judicial Sentence;</hi> it being commonly the Mark of Innocency, where it dwells, notwithſtanding the many Attempts made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65035:13"/> it, to be plain and ſimple, and eaſy in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of it ſelf to the protection of him, who hath given Men the greateſt aſſurance, he will not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally leave it, but vigorouſly plead its Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Thus having given the Reaſons that induce me to believe there is ſuch a Sin, as I have mentioned, ſome of thoſe committed to my Charge, may be Guilty of: I come in the next place to Conſider what plauſible Defence they may make for themſelves, and what fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies they may probably put upon their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, to lay the Clamours of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First</hi> then, It may probably be ſaid, That ſure if People had been Guilty of ſuch a Sin as this, and continued Unrepenting of it, as I ſay, all perſons that are Guilty of it, and do not make Reſtitution, do, That their own Conſciences muſt, ere this, have flown in their Faces, and made them viſibly uneaſy to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; that ere this <hi>God</hi> would have ſhew'd His Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them, rendered ſucceſsleſs all their <hi>Counſels,</hi> and brought them at the feet of their Adverſaries: Whereas the quite contrary Appears; great cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life, and a proſperity, ſo far from a ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Adverſaries, that it ſeems rather mounted over them.</p>
            <p>To all which, I thus Anſwer, That all theſe, Silence of Conſcience (which yet, they know beſt who are the Owners of them, how ſilent they be; they may be vocal, and loud enough to them, though nor vocal, nor viſible to others;) I ſay, that Silence of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a proſperous outward Eſtate, are but very fallacious Grounds to determine the good Eſtate of the Soul by; ſo far from being competent Arguments to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65035:13"/> that purpoſe, that they may attend the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eſtate of the Soul, that of Dereliction; for beſides that, there may be many ways uſed, whereby Men may be diverted from attending to the Clamours of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conſequently made to think it cannot ſpeak, becauſe they do not hearken unto it. We read in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ of a <hi>Seared Conſcience,</hi> from whoſe not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe it hath loſt feeling, we ought not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all is well with it.</p>
            <p>And for ſucceſs of <hi>Counſels,</hi> and proſperity of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Eſtate, which alſo may be ſometime more Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of <hi>God</hi>'s diſpleaſure, leaving Men to all the Temptations of that Fortune, than his approbation of their practices; That they are not the peculiar Lot of the Righteous, I leave <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> Father and Son, to ſatisfy all the Fathers and Sons upon the Earth; the Firſt in the 37th. <hi>Pſalm, ver.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of him, who proſpereth in his way, becauſe of the Man, who bringeth wicked Devices to paſs. Ceaſe from Anger, and forſake Wrath; Fret not thy ſelf in any wiſe to do Evil; For evil-doers ſhall be cut off,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But yet a little while, and the Wicked ſhall not be,</hi> &amp;c. For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time then, in <hi>David</hi>'s judgement, the Wicked may bring their Counſels to paſs, and proſper in their way. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.20. to the ſame purpoſe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpoke before, <hi>The Candle of the Wicked ſhall be put out,</hi> that is, The Splendor of his Eſtate ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever; which ſuppoſes he may ſome time have it. What may happen to the Unrighteous and the Wicked, as well as the Juſt and the Godly, ought not to be taken up as Arguments of the Welfare of the Soul, and the perſon's acceptance with <hi>God.</hi> But in caſe a perſon's Conſcience be ſuffered to ſpeak, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65035:14"/> that, at leaſtwiſe, inwardly, one may be convinced of ſuch a Guilt; yet it is not impoſſible, but he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude himſelf with an opinion, that he is not obliged to make Reſtitution, becauſe that of that he hath wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully detained, he hath made no benefit, but that it proved an occaſion of real diſadvantage to him; as for illuſtration, Suppoſe the Chief Magiſtrate of any Town in Chriſtendom, had, by vertue of his place, received ſo much Money for the Publick, but laid them out on, or reſerved them for his proper uſe: ſuppoſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon, out of his averſneſs to ſuch a practice, (from what principles or motives ſoever, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe is not material) ſhould uſe a legal courſe to recover thoſe out of his hands, in fencing of the Man's ſelf, againſt which, it might coſt him as much as the firſt Sum in queſtion came to, and, it may be, more; What? Are the Caſes of Conſcience ſo ſevere and ſtrict, as to require a <hi>Restitution,</hi> when the Man is ſatisfied he hath expended the Sum, and it may be, qy oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it, as much again of his own? This, it may be, will be anſwered with ſomething the ſame ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that is in the ſlothful Servant's Anſwer to his Maſter in the Goſpel, of a natural auſterity in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actor.</hi> This I do the rather take notice of, becauſe I have heard what to me ſeemed to glance that way. But the Reſolution of this will be eaſy, if you put it to the rule of plain and common Debt, where you know, the Debt is never reckoned the more paid, for any charges the obſtinate refuſal of paying, may occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; there is an increaſe of obſtinacy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſomeneſs, none of ſatisfaction made by that means. Shall any Man lay out my Right in the defence of his own Obſtinacy or Covetouſneſs, and ſhall he reckon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65035:14"/> it paid, becauſe at long running he got nothing by it? He that can ſpy a ſubſtantial difference, whereby it may be more a Plea in one, than the other, hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faculty of ſeeing, than either Reaſon or Religion furniſh him with.</p>
            <p>Having ſo given the Reaſons, that induced me to believe ſome Men guilty, and anſwered what they may probably offer for themſelves to ſtave off their concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the matter of detaining the Right of others; I ſhould come next to do the ſame, touching injuries done to the Bodies and good Names of Perſons. As to the <hi>Firſt</hi> whereof, I ſhall only ſay, there have been here ſome Injuries done to ſome in that, by whom I know not, and it may be a great deal more, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I heard of: Let every Man examine his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and remember, and uſe a while the Rule given, touching <hi>Restitution</hi> in that caſe.</p>
            <p>And as to the Guilt of the Abuſe of the good Names of People, I ſhall ſay little more, then read you the Character Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> gave an odd Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men in his time, and truſt any Body in the Congregation, that knows them, to find out the Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by it:<note n="‖" place="margin">Arch-Biſh-<hi>Whitgift's</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 423.</note> 
               <hi>It is their manner (Abuſe</hi> he meant) <hi>except you pleaſe their humour in all things, deſerve never ſo well, all is nothing with them, but they will deprive you, rail on you, back-bite you, invent Lies of you, and ſpread falſe Rumours, as though you were the vileſt Perſon upon the Earth.</hi> I muſt confeſs, had I met with this, any time theſe <hi>Twelve</hi> Months hereabouts, in any new Writing, and been left to gueſs whence it came, I had concluded it had been ſome Bodies obſervation of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I knew well enough; But I heartily pray <hi>God</hi> to forgive them, and in order to His forgiveneſs, to give
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65035:15"/> them the Grace of hearty Repentance, ſuch as may ſignify its ſeriouſneſs, by ſuch <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of the good Name of every abuſed Perſon, as they may be able to make, and <hi>God</hi> may pleaſe to accept of.</p>
            <p>Thus far have I diſcharged the Office of a faithful <hi>Chirurgeon,</hi> ſhewed and ſearched an <hi>Old Wound,</hi> and preſcribed the Means of its Cure; and I am afraid, not without extreamly angering my <hi>Patients.</hi> I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, in caſe of the Guilt of Injury, the indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Neceſſity of <hi>Reſtitution;</hi> the extent of its Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to Perſons and Things, with the meaſure of <hi>Reſtitution</hi> required in all matters of Wrong: I have brought it home to your doors, and ſhewed you the Reaſons I had to lay it there. The abſolute Neceſſity of <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> I intimated from the Danger of Eternal Damnation. And becauſe that may not ſo nearly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Men, though it infinitely moſt deſerves their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I could give you both inſtances, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Threats of <hi>God</hi>'s ſignal appearances in this World, in the Vindication of the <hi>Oppreſſed Stranger,</hi> the <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> the <hi>Widow,</hi> and the <hi>Poor,</hi> when the beſt-ſpun Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of Men will be unravelled and defeated; and read you dreadful Things out of the 20th. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the 4th. <hi>verſ.</hi> of it: But inſtead of all that, I ſhall recommend to your conſideration an expreſſion of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> reſolved into a Sentence, <hi>When God ariſes, His Enemies will be ſcattered;</hi> which will be, when He ariſes in Judgment, either here, or hereafter, or both, for ſometime he will; for he ſaith, <hi>He heareth the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Poor, and that the Poor ſhall not be forſaken for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, before I have done, I judge it neceſſary to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65035:15"/> two or three Objections, which, I foreſee, will, in all probability, be levelled againſt this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>One, That it is a very unſeaſonable Diſcourſe, and but a courſe Entertainment of a Perſon newly entered up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Office.</p>
            <p>To that I ſay, That that never ſeems to me unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that is neceſſary, and that I apprehend not the incivility of catching hold of the Skirt of a Man's beſt Weed, tho a Robe of Scarlet, if I ſuſpect he runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fire with it.</p>
            <p>The next I can think of, is, That it is ill becoming a Miniſter of Peace, to diſturb a new-made Peace, with the Repreſentation of old matters of Diſſention, which no doubt will, with all the aggravations, ſpleen and malice can ſuggeſt, be repreſented.</p>
            <p>But to this, I beg leave to diſtinguiſh between true Peace, and the varniſh and imagery of it. It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Combination of Men, that hath juſt pretenſions to the glorious title of Peace. We read of a Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> upon the ſorry occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Condemning the innocenteſt Perſon in the World; but no where any reaſons to Applaud it. There are ſome Unions look more like Conſpiracies, than Peace. Is this Peace to huſh up all former Injuries to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and to capacitate Men's ſelves without damage, to Act, as many more, as they have a mind to? The Anſwer <hi>Jehu</hi> made the Son of <hi>Ahab,</hi> enquiring for Peace, was, <hi>What Peace, as long as thy Mother</hi> Jezabel<hi>'s Whoredomes, and Witchcrafts are ſo many?</hi> And may not there, think you, a queſtion ſomething like it be ask'd here? <hi>What Peace, as long as Wrongs and Injuries continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied for?</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us, that <hi>God</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no Peace to the Wicked;</hi> and do you now judge,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65035:16"/> whether ſuch Crimes as <hi>Irreſtitution</hi> or <hi>Perjury,</hi> may not rank Men, of what advance ſoever, amongſt them?</p>
            <p>A well-founded Peace, there is no Man, I hope, I may truly ſay it, wiſhes more than my ſelf; but in order to it, muſt adviſe you, to be at Peace with <hi>God</hi> and your own Conſciences; and that you may ſo, to remove from amongſt you <hi>The Accurſed Thing,</hi> which will prove a more ſolid Foundation for a laſting Peace, than any thing that I know hath hitherto been propoſed, or happened to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Re-eſtabliſhment of it; without which, all this Pageantry will look more like a triumph over Juſtice and Honeſty, than true Peace.</p>
            <p>One Objection more againſt what I have delivered, I ſuppoſe, will be, That I ſpoke out of Envy and Malice, and upon Provocation.</p>
            <p>If what I have already ſaid to that upon my entrance into this Diſcourſe, do not acquit me, I ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf much more; only ſay, be my Motive to, or occaſion of it what it will, if I have ſaid a truth, that will juſtify no Man's non-obſervance of it. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the <hi>First Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Philipians,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Some Preached Chriſt, even of Envy and Strife, verſe</hi> the <hi>Fifteenth;</hi> however, <hi>verſe</hi> the <hi>Eighteenth, He Rejoyced;</hi> and the <hi>Nineteenth, Was perſwaded it would turn to his Salvation.</hi> Holy <hi>David</hi> was more afraid of the <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Balms</hi> of <hi>Flatterers,</hi> than the <hi>Wounds</hi> of his <hi>Friends,</hi> whom if they had not been in their intentions, ſuch he would doubtleſs in effect have made, by uſeing their Counſels for his good. The Enmity I have to you, diſpenſes with my wiſhing you may make as wiſe uſe of what I delivered, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or holy <hi>David</hi> did, or would have done, of Truths delivered by an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. If <hi>For telling you the Truth, I am become more your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65035:16"/> Enemy,</hi> and increaſed your unkindneſs towards me; try whether you can ſpight me, or ſhew it in avoiding what is in mine, and the judgment of the whole world, the greateſt of Evils, Eternal Damnation, by a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſignificant <hi>Repentance;</hi> which <hi>God,</hi> I heartily pray it, Grant you, and that what hath been delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may not be the <hi>Savour of Death unto Death,</hi> unto any, but the <hi>Savour of Life unto Life,</hi> to all that hear me; wherewith I conclude.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
